Okay, so in this video
we're going to talk about a
tooling technique called
resource optimization, right?
Resource optimization techniques.
Now, resource optimization is considered a
tooling technique of schedule management.
So in the old Pinbox six,
old Pinbox six standards,
this would be considered
a tooling technique.
It's actually a tooling technique of
developed schedule.
Now, resource optimization is
actually pretty much common
sense, something that most
of you guys do all the time.
You probably just didn't realize it's
actually a name for it.
And that is basically making sure that all
resources are utilized
at the optimum level.
Making sure no resources are overutilized
or underutilized.
All equipment, supplies,
labor, raw materials,
they're all utilized at the optimum level.
And then you're going to be making
adjustments.
to make sure that resource is utilized at
the optimum level.
So, as a very simple example, you're
managing a project, right?
You've got several teams on your project.
You see one team that's putting in tons
and tons of hours of overtime,
right, 60, 70 hours of work
a week, and you see other
teams that are barely
putting in 35 hours a week.
Well, are you going to do something about
that, right?
You've got, you know, some teams,
you've got one team that is way
overutilized, other teams that are way
underutilized.
you know, you're going to do something
about that.
You're going to move activities around.
You're going to move team members around
so that all teams, all resource in this
case, are going to be utilised at the most
optimal level.
And that's basically what resource
optimization is.
So as a very, very simple example here,
let's just say we're looking at one
particular employee, looking at one
particular team.
This is a very oversimplification,
but it kind of homes in on the point.
So let's say we're just looking at one
particular team member, right?
One employee, employee eight.
And we're seeing how has
their work been allocated,
you know, over these
next few weeks, right?
So on the x-axis, we've got the weeks,
week one, week two, week three,
all the way to week six.
Right.
And then on the y-axis, we've got the
number of hours per week, right?
So optimally, this person needs to be
allocated 40 hours of work a week.
So we see on week one and week three and
week six, this person has been,
you know, allocated to the optimum level,
40 hours of work.
But we see on week two and week five,
this person is underutilized, only 30
hours a week, and then week four all of a
sudden, way overutilized, you know,
80 hours a week.
So we might do something about that.
So week four, this person will be way
overutilized.
Maybe some of these activities can be
pushed forward to week two.
Are we going to make some adjustments,
right?
Some of these week three
activities move to week
two, some of the week
four move to week three.
Some of them we can move over into week
five and so on and so forth.
So basically we're trying to avoid these
peaks and valleys so that in this case,
the work for this employee is going to be
utilized at the optimum level.
Now obviously this was a very,
very simple example, right, when we're
looking at the team overall, I want to
look at the team overall, make sure all
team members, all teams are optimally
utilized when we're looking at machines,
when we're looking at raw materials and so
and so forth, so forth.
We're looking at all resources here.
So resource optimization refers to both
physical resources as
well as team resources.
Now there are two types of resource
optimization techniques, right?
There's two types.
One is known as resource leveling and the
other one is resource smoothing.
So we've got resource leveling and
resource smoothing.
Now, resource leveling is specifically
readjusting the start and end dates,
like readjusting your schedule based on
availability of resources, based on
availability of machines and so and so
forth.
So just a very simple example,
right?
Let's say you've got one team.
member, there's these
some certain activities
that only this one team
member can perform.
But that team member has limited
availability.
That team member is not available whenever
you need them.
That team member is only available,
you know, for a certain time period.
So all of those activities that that team
member can perform, like you are going to
schedule just at the point when that team
member is available.
So let's say you've already developed your
schedule.
You've developed your schedule with the
assumption that this team member can be
available will be available whenever you
need them.
But then you find out after
developing the schedule that
team member is actually not
available whenever you need them.
They're only available for a certain time
period.
Now you need to readjust your schedule.
You're going to have to
go back and these activities
are dependent on other
activities and so and so forth.
You basically want to readjust your
schedule so that these activities are
performed just when that team member is
available.
You may end up changing your critical
path.
You may end up going behind schedule.
So resource leveling then, basically you
may end up changing the critical path.
You may end up extending the schedule.
So the whole idea of resource leveling is
to make sure that resources are not
overutilize, underutilized, they're not
double booked and so on and so forth.
Resource smoothing, on the other hand,
you can make some adjustments,
you can make these adjustments, but
only within the amount of float, right?
So basically, you cannot go behind
schedule.
So you can move resources from critical
path activities, or rather move resources
from non-critical path activities to
critical path activities, right?
So, but you cannot go behind schedule.
So that's the difference between resource
leveling and resource smoothing.
Resource leveling, a lot of
times you end up going behind
schedule, resource smoothing,
you cannot go behind schedule.
So these two then are both known as
resource optimization techniques.